<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preach'd before the Right Honourable Lord-Mayor, the Aldermen, and citizens of London, at St. Mary Le Bow, on Thursday, November 5, 1696 by Samuel Bradford ...</title>
            <author>Bradford, Samuel, 1652-1731.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 52 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29106</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4119</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19690</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12115728</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12115728</idno>
            <idno type="VID">54293</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29106)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 54293)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 759:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preach'd before the Right Honourable Lord-Mayor, the Aldermen, and citizens of London, at St. Mary Le Bow, on Thursday, November 5, 1696 by Samuel Bradford ...</title>
                  <author>Bradford, Samuel, 1652-1731.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 26 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for B. Aylmer ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Romans III, 8 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="order">
            <pb facs="tcp:54293:1"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>CLARKE, Mayor.</salute>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Martis decimo die Novembr'</hi> 1696. <hi>Anno<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> R. Rs.</hi> Wilhelmi <hi>Tertii, Angliae, &amp;c. Octavo.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>THis Court doth deſire Mr. <hi>Bradford</hi> to Print his Sermon preach'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Right Honourable the Lord-Mayor, Aldermen, and Citizens of this City, at the Pariſh-Church of St. <hi>Mary-le-Bow,</hi> on <hi>Thurſday</hi> laſt, being the Fifth of this Inſtant <hi>November.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>GOODFELLOW.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:54293:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preach'd before the Right Honourable the Lord-Mayor, THE ALDERMEN, AND Citizens of <hi>LONDON,</hi> At St. <hi>MARY LE BOW,</hi> On <hi>Thurſday, November</hi> 5. 1696.</p>
            <p>By <hi>SAMUEL BRADFORD,</hi> RECTOR of the ſaid Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>B. Aylmer,</hi> at the <hi>Three Pigeons</hi> againſt the <hi>Royal Exchange</hi> in <hi>Cornhill.</hi> MDCXCVII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:54293:2"/>
            <p>Mr. <hi>BRADFORD</hi>'s SERMON Preach'd before the <hi>Lord-Mayor,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>November</hi> the Fifth, 1696.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:54293:3"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:54293:3"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:54293:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:54293:4"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable Sir <hi>EDWARD CLARKE,</hi> Lord-Mayor of the City of <hi>London,</hi> AND THE Court of Aldermen.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IN Obedience to Your Commands, I preſent You with this Plain Diſcourſe, heartily wiſhing it may be of Uſe to thoſe Ends for which I preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it.</p>
            <p>I charitably believe, That the greater part of thoſe who yet remain diſſatisfied with the Eſtabliſhment we are under, are not ſo from Malice, but from Preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice; and that if they could once get into a juſt way of Thinking calmly and ſedately, they would ſoon change their preſent Opinions. This I have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd to lead them to, without giving them any juſt Cauſe of Offence, whereby to increaſe their Prejudices, inſtead of removing them.</p>
            <p>Could we of this Nation once again be ſo happy, as to become thoroughly <hi>One Body,</hi> both as <hi>Members
<pb facs="tcp:54293:5"/>of Society,</hi> and as <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> as it would be one of the beſt Expreſſions of our Gratitude to Almighty God, for the many Deliverances he hath granted us; ſo it would be the ſhrewdeſt Revenge we could take upon our <hi>Romiſh</hi> Adverſaries, and effectually diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearten them from attempting any farther upon us.</p>
            <p>I am perſuaded, that the Greater Part of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in general, and of this City in particular, ſtand well-diſpos'd towards ſuch an Union; and 'tis pity that the <hi>Weakneſs</hi> of ſome, and the <hi>Deſign</hi> of others, ſhould hinder the Effect.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Your Lordſhip</hi> is what I would perſuade others to be; I mean, An Hearty and Conſtant Friend to the <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State;</hi> and Your <hi>Practice,</hi> as well as Your <hi>Profeſſion,</hi> exemplifies what in this Diſcourſe I aim at.</p>
            <p>That it may pleaſe Almighty God to Preſerve, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect, and Bleſs <hi>Your Lordſhip,</hi> and by his good Providence to Increaſe the Number of ſuch Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, is the Prayer of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute> 
               <signed>Your moſt Faithful and Humble Servant, <hi>SAMUEL BRADFORD.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:54293:5"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preach'd before the Lord-Mayor, &amp;c.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ROM. III. 8.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And not rather, as we be ſlanderouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, and as ſome affirm that we ſay, Let us do Evil, that Good may come; whoſe Damnation is juſt.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Double Occaſion of this Day's Solemnity, moved me to treat on theſe Words; which will naturally lead me both to condemn that accurſed Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple upon which the avow'd Enemies of our Church and Nation acted on the former of theſe Occaſions; as alſo to vindicate our ſelves from the Calumny which ſome have ſpread about concerning us, as if we had acted upon the ſame Principle, on the latter of them.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:54293:6"/>
            <p> In the days of our Fathers, the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> form'd a Plot againſt us for the ſubverting our Government, and eſpecially for the changing our Religion; in order to which excellent Ends (as they accounted them) they did not ſtick at making uſe of the vileſt Means that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Men or Devils could invent. But that Divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence which hath from one Age to another taken eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Care of us, diſcover'd their Deſign, and by that means defeated it; and this in ſo conſpicuous a manner, that it was then, and has been ever ſince generally own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, with Thankfulneſs to Almighty God, and with Deteſtation both of the Contrivance it ſelf, and of the Principle from which it proceeded.</p>
            <p>In our own days, the ſame ſort of men had again form'd a very dangerous Deſign againſt us, and by other Methods hoped to bring about the ſame End. But in this Inſtance alſo the Providence of God hath given them a very remarkable Diſappointment; which altho it be likewiſe by the Body of the Nation thankfully aſcribed to Almighty God, as the Great Author of our Deliverance; yet there are not wanting ſome, even amongſt our ſelves, that charge us with having uſed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful Means for the attaining a good End; and openly declare againſt our annexing the <hi>Second</hi> Occaſion of this Day's Thankſgiving to the <hi>Firſt;</hi> as if in doing ſo, we were guilty of a manifeſt Contradiction.</p>
            <p>It ſeems highly reaſonable therefore, when we are aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled in this Solemn Manner to offer up our devout Thanks to God for the Deliverance he hath reiterated to us, to vindicate our ſelves from ſo groſs an Abſurdity; and to make it evident, that in Both theſe Inſtances we have great reaſon to give Thanks to God, and that we may with a good Conſcience aſcribe our Deliverance to Him in the <hi>Later</hi> Caſe, as well as in the <hi>Former.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:54293:6"/>
            <p> The Words of the Text are St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s, and the Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of them was this. The Apoſtle in his preceding Diſcourſe had been intimating, That the <hi>Jews</hi> by diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believing the Goſpel of our Saviour,
<note place="margin">V. 3.</note> had not <hi>made void the faithfulneſs of God;</hi> nay, on the contrary, That <hi>their unrighteouſneſs did commend the righteouſneſs of God;</hi>
               <note place="margin">V. 5.</note> that is, it render'd it more conſpicuous and illuſtrious. Upon which he brings in the <hi>Jew</hi> objecting, <hi>But if our unrighteouſneſs commend the righteouſneſs of God, what ſhall we ſay? Is God unrighteous, who taketh venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance?</hi> That is, How can God juſtly puniſh thoſe, who by their Iniquity advance his Glory? To this he anſwers with abhorrence (it being an Objection ſo plainly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable, that it needed not be confuted by Argument, but only diſclaim'd), <hi>God forbid;</hi>
               <note place="margin">V. 6.</note> 
               <hi>for then how ſhall God judge the world?</hi> That is, If he were chargeable with Unrighteouſneſs, how could he be a fit Governor or Judge of the World? For <hi>ſhall not the Judge of all the earth do right?</hi> But here he goes on with the <hi>Jews</hi> Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection;
<note place="margin">V. 7, 8.</note> 
               <hi>If the truth of God hath more abounded through my lye unto his glory, why yet am I alſo judged as a ſinner; and not rather, as we be ſlanderouſly reported, and as ſome af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm that we ſay. Let us do evil, that good may come?</hi> That is, If the Truth of God be render'd more illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous by the Falſeneſs of Men, with what Juſtice can the man that is thus falſe, be dealt with as a ſinner? Seeing his falſeneſs is a means of bringing Glory to God, ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it can be no Crime. Why may we not rather argue thus <hi>Let us do evil, that good may come?</hi> This, ſays he, we Apoſtles, and particularly I <hi>Paul,</hi> are <hi>ſlanderouſly reported to ſay; ſome affirm that we do ſay ſo,</hi> either directly, or at leaſt by conſequence<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> It may be they might not have ſo little honeſty, as to charge them with ſaying it expreſly; however, they charged it as a neceſſary Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:54293:7"/>upon the Doctrine which they taught: To which he again replies, not by Arguing, but by De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation, <hi>Whoſe Damnation is juſt. Whoſe Damnation;</hi> that is, <hi>Theirs,</hi> whoſoever they are, that either own, or act upon ſuch a Principle as this, <hi>That it is lawful to do evil, that good may come;</hi> or <hi>Theirs,</hi> who thus calumni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate us, as if this Principle were ours; that is, as if this were a Chriſtian Principle, either taught or allowed by the Apoſtles of our Lord: For the word <hi>Whoſe,</hi> may refer to either of them. This I take to be the plain meaning of the Words; from which we may make theſe <hi>Three</hi> Obſervations, which are evidently contained or implied in them.</p>
            <p n="1">I. That Almighty God can, and often doth over rule the evil Actions of men to his own Glory, and cauſe bad Means to conduce to a good End.</p>
            <p n="2">II. That notwithſtanding this, 'tis a deteſtable and damnable Principle, <hi>That unlawful Means may be uſed, in order to the bringing about an End that is good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">III. That it is moreover a <hi>ſlanderous,</hi> and therefore a very <hi>unjuſt</hi> and <hi>deteſtable</hi> Practice, to charge this Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple upon thoſe who not only diſown it, but whoſe Actions have given no juſt occaſion for ſuch an Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</p>
            <p>Of each of theſe I deſign to diſcourſe briefly, and as I go along, apply them to the Occaſions of our preſent meeting.</p>
            <p n="1">I. That Almighty God can, and often doth over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rule the evil Actions of men to his own Glory, and cauſe bad Means to conduce to a good End.</p>
            <p>This is ſufficiently intimated in our Apoſtle's Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe at the beginning of this Chapter; and his aſſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this, was (as I have ſhewn) that which gave oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:54293:7"/>to the Reflection made in the Text. The <hi>Jews</hi> had been favoured by God with eſpecial Advantages for the knowing the Meſſias, when he ſhould appear amongſt them; yet we know how they disbeliev'd and rejected him, when he did appear, even to the ruin of their Church and Nation. But yet this their Sin illuſtrated the Glory of God's Juſtice, in puniſhing them ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markably for their heinous Crime; and by giving occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion alſo to the Apoſtles <hi>to turn from them to the Gentiles;</hi> it proved a means of advancing God's Glory, by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagating the knowledge of him in the world. The <hi>Gentiles</hi> on the other hand had been grievous Sinners, not only ſtrangers to the living and true God, but living in open violation of thoſe Laws which he had given them in their very Natures; yet upon their hearing the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Doctrine preach'd, many of them embrac'd it with great readineſs; which likewiſe gave occaſion to the magnifying the Grace of God towards them, in pardoning their paſt Offences, and receiving them into his favour, upon their Repentance and Amendment; which again prov'd another occaſion of the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ws</hi> blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the Doctrine of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and imputing to him falſly the ſame Principle which they here do in the Text; as he ſeems to intimate in that Paſſage, <hi>Rom</hi> 6.1. <hi>What ſhall we ſay then? Shall we continue in ſin, that grace may abound?</hi> Anſwering there, as he does here, by rejecting ſuch a Poſition with Abhorrence, <hi>God forbid.</hi> Indeed as to both theſe Inſtances, St. <hi>Paul</hi> afterwards in this ſame Epiſtle reſolves the whole of God's Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation into Infinite Wiſdom, when ſpeaking both of the Sin of the <hi>Jews</hi> in rejecting, and the Happineſs of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> in embracing the Goſpel of our Saviour, he concludes, <hi>chap.</hi> 11.33, 36. <hi>Oh the depth of the riches both of the wiſdom and knowledge of God! how unſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:54293:8"/>are his judgments, and his ways paſt finding out! for of him, and through him, and to him are all things; to whom be glory forever.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <p>Whoever is acquainted with the Hiſtory of the Holy Scriptures, needs not be at much pains to find out abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of Inſtances of the like kind. And if we would reflect upon one that has a fair Reſemblance to thoſe which I ſhall have occaſion preſently to mention from among our ſelves, it may be that in the Book of <hi>Eſther;</hi> which Book was written on purpoſe to declare the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Goodneſs of God, in over-ruling the Pride and Malice of a wicked man, to his own Glory, and the Good of his Church; ordering it ſo, that the Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor ſhould erect a Gallows for himſelf to be hang'd on; and that he ſhould by Lot chuſe out a Month and a Day for the deſtruction of the Nation and Church of the <hi>Jews,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſth. 9.22.</note> which did in effect prove <hi>the day in which the Jews reſted from their enemies, and the month which was turned unto them from ſorrow into joy, and from mourning into a good day;</hi> as we read in the Sequel of that Hiſtory.</p>
            <p>But to paſs by all other Inſtances that might be given, we Chriſtians have one at hand, which may ſerve in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of all, namely, When the greateſt Sin that ever was committed, the Crucifying the Son of God, was by the Divine Wiſdom and Goodneſs over-ruled, to become a Means of the greateſt Good that was ever conferr'd upon the Children of Men, <hi>viz.</hi> putting them into a new Capacity of Eternal Life and Happineſs.</p>
            <p>And the reaſon of all this is evident. That Being, who ſeeth all things at one view; who not only know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth what is now doing, but what will be done, nay, what will be attempted or deſign'd hereafter; who farther diſcerneth the tendency of every Action, and what will be the natural Conſequence of it; and who
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:54293:8"/>at the ſame time hath all Power in his Hands, ſo that he can either permit or prevent the Execution of any Deſign; can Confirm or Annul every Purpoſe and Intention: He certainly can eaſily out-wit and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reach the craftieſt and the worſt of Men, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently can diſpoſe and order what they intend wickedly or fooliſhly, to quite other purpoſes than what were in their Hearts. And foraſmuch as his Goodneſs is equal to his Power and Wiſdom, we may ſafely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that as he can, ſo he will govern Affairs in ſuch wiſe, as to bring good out of evil. As we may rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably argue from the Perfection of his Nature, that he never would have permitted Evil to have come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world, unleſs he could have over-rul'd it to ſome wiſe and good ends: So we may alſo, That he never will permit any of his Creatures to do that evil thing, which he cannot, and which he will not make to iſſue in the Glory of his Holy Name, and the Good of his Creation.</p>
            <p>And now if we would apply this to our preſent pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, it will not be difficult. That the Conſpiracy of <hi>this Day</hi> in the time of our Fathers was a Notorious Wickedneſs, I will at preſent take for granted; and if it were, I am ſure it prov'd an Eminent occaſion alſo of God's Manifeſting the Glory of ſeveral of his Attributes. His Wiſdom, for inſtance, evidently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd, in permitting the Conſpirators to proceed juſt to Execution, and then all on a ſudden diſcovering their dark Deſigns, nay, making one of themſelves the occaſion of this Diſcovery. His Juſtice was manifeſt, in turning the Miſchief upon themſelves, and ſubject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to the Puniſhment which their Crime de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd. His Goodneſs was very conſpicuous in ſaving the Lives of ſo many innocent Perſons, deſign'd as a
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:54293:9"/>Sacrifice to the cruel Zeal of thoſe Ungodly Men, and in preſerving, together with them, the Liberty and the Religion of our Nation. Nor was this all; but this Conſpiracy farther redounded to the Glory of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, as it became a means of begetting in the People of this Land an honeſt Averſion to that Church, which allow'd and encourag'd ſuch Wicked and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive Enterprizes as this: And perhaps the keeping <hi>this Day</hi> for ſo many Years together, in Memory of ſo remarkable a Deliverance from ſo Barbarous a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, did in an eſpecial manner help towards the keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Nation awake, and rendring them conſtantly jealous of whatſoever plauſible Pretences that Church might make for the future. I am ſure in the I ate Reign, when we were in freſh danger from the ſame Quarter, the Zealous Obſervation of <hi>this Day,</hi> and the Diſcourſes that were Preach'd and Printed upon this Occaſion, were of very conſiderable Uſe.</p>
            <p>And if we paſs from <hi>that,</hi> to the other Occaſion of our preſent Aſſembling, we ſhall find a new Inſtance among our ſelves, of God's over ruling the Evil Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Men to his own Glory. Our Enemies indeed, in this later Caſe, were ſo fair, as to deal more above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board with us, and plainly to let us know what they were deſigning; and perhaps they will juſtify them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves as leſs wicked, becauſe more open in their At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt. But whoever well conſiders the Illegal and Unrighteous Practices that were uſed, in order to the ſubverting the Legal Government of this Kingdom, and rooting out God's true Religion from among us, may ſee cauſe enough to own the Divine Wiſdom and Goodneſs, in bringing Good out of Evil in this inſtance alſo.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:54293:9"/>
            <p>'Twas the Effect of no leſs than Divine Wiſdom, to bring about our Deliverance at a time, when we were ſo cloſely beſet on all ſides, as to have no viſible way of Eſcaping left us. When after the Endeavours of many Years, all things at laſt ſeem'd to Conſpire to the effecting what our Enemies had Deſign'd, when they were confident of Succeſs, and began to Triumph over us, as already in their Power; it pleaſed God all on a ſudden to give ſuch an unexpected Turn to Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, that inſtead of a Lawleſs Power, and the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Religion being ſetled among us, they were by a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence of divers Cauſes, render'd more unlikely to prevail for the future, than ever. The Government chang'd from Popiſh to Proteſtant; the Strength of the Kingdom given over into other Hands; many Wholeſome and Neceſſary Laws made to prevent the like Danger hereafter, which we had then incur'd; And this Kingdom, which ſeem'd the only One want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to turn the Balance of <hi>Europe,</hi> and which was then in a fair way to have done it, made to become the Great Bulwark of the Liberties of all <hi>Europe,</hi> and the main Support of the Proteſtant Religion in the World. And ſo much may ſuffice for the Firſt Obſervation I laid down. I proceed to the</p>
            <p n="2">II. <hi>Viz.</hi> That notwithſtanding all this, 'tis a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable and Damnable Principle, <hi>That <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawful means may be uſed, in order to the bringing about an End that is good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You ſee with what Abhorrence the Apoſtle in the Text diſclaims it; adding, That <hi>their Damnation is juſt,</hi> who either avow or act upon it. 'Tis in truth ſuch an open Defiance to God and Goodneſs; ſuch a flat Contradiction to Truth and Reaſon, as well as to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:54293:10"/>that it very well became him thus to expreſs himſelf concerning it.</p>
            <p>The ſame Apoſtle has elſewhere likewiſe teſtified his Senſe of this Matter; namely, When giving an Account of his own Behaviour, before he became a Chriſtian, he ſays, That <hi>he verily thought that he ought to do</hi> what he did <hi>contrary to the Name of Jeſus,</hi> viz. <hi>Shutting up many of his Saints in Priſon; giving his Voice againſt them, when they were put to Death; puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them oft in every Synagogue, and compelling them to Blaſpheme; and being exceedingly mad againſt them, and perſecuting them into ſtrange Cities,</hi> Acts 26, 9, 10, 11. All theſe things, he ſays, <hi>he verily thought that he ought to do;</hi> and yet for having done this, he arraigns him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, in another place, as <hi>a Blaſphemer, a Perſecutor, and Injurious,</hi> 1 Tim. 1.13. Which Crimes he accuſes himſelf of, not (as it may be objected) meerly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Chriſtian Religion, which he thus <hi>madly</hi> op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, prov'd to be God's true Religion; but more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over becauſe he uſed irregular and unlawful Methods in oppoſing it, even though it had been a falſe Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, as he then ſuppos'd it was. If the Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion had not been from God, he had not then indeed been <hi>a Blaſphemer,</hi> as he here calls himſelf; but he would nevertheleſs have been <hi>a Perſecutor,</hi> and <hi>an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious Perſon,</hi> in dealing ſo hardly and inhumanly with thoſe, who ſincerely and honeſtly Profeſs'd it, and were otherwiſe perfectly Innocent, and Inoffen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive; nay Righteous, and Holy Men.</p>
            <p>Our Bleſſed Saviour hath in like manner declar'd his Senſe to the ſame purpoſe, when ſpeaking to his Diſciples, he telleth them, That the <hi>Jews,</hi> after his departure from them, <hi>would put them out of their Synagogues,</hi> and not content with that, <hi>That the time
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:54293:10"/>would come, that whoſoever ſhould kill them, ſhould think that he did God ſervice,</hi> John 16.2. And this our Lord not only foretells that the <hi>Jews</hi> would do, but he ſpeaks of it as an heinous Crime in them; for ſo it follows, <hi>Ver.</hi> 3. <hi>And theſe things will they do unto you, becauſe they have not known the Father, nor me. They have not known me;</hi> elſe they would not deal thus deſpitefully and cruelly with my Servants: And <hi>they have not known my father;</hi> elſe they would not do ſuch Acts of Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, ſuch unrighteous and unnatural things, to inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent and honeſt Men, under a pretence of ſerving him, and promoting his Glory.</p>
            <p>And as the <hi>New,</hi> ſo the <hi>Old</hi> Teſtament alſo hath fully born it's Teſtimony againſt this deteſtable Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, of <hi>doing Evil, that Good may come.</hi> We have a remarkable Paſſage in the Book of <hi>Job,</hi> utter'd by <hi>Job</hi> himſelf, who was not ſo much as initiated in the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Religion, but as far as appears, was a pious and good Man, upon the Principles of Natural Religion only; which Paſſage being Recorded in the Canon of the Old Teſtament, is a full proof, that God hath both in Nature, and under the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Diſpenſation, as well as by Chriſtianity, declar'd his diſallowance of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple I am ſpeaking of. The words of <hi>Job</hi> are theſe, which he ſpake in the bitterneſs of his Soul, when his Friends unkindly charg'd him with Hypocriſy, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending thereby to Apologize for God, in laying ſuch heavy Afflictions upon him, <hi>Job</hi> 13.7, 8. <hi>Will you,</hi> ſays he, <hi>ſpeak wickedly for God, and talk deceitfully for him? Will ye accept his Perſon? Will ye contend for God?</hi> He declares, you ſee, againſt going about to ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtify even God himſelf, by lying and falſehood. Not that God Almighty can ever be ſuppos'd to need ſuch a juſtification: But <hi>Job</hi> ſignifies moreover his Abhorrence
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:54293:11"/>of it, and that he would be very far from approving what they did, (though they ſeem to have been other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe too good men, to have done this knowingly and wilfully;) He therefore adds in the words following, V. 9, 10, 11. <hi>Is it good that he ſhould ſearch you out? Or as one man mocketh another, do ye ſo mock him?</hi> To Lye for God, is it ſeems <hi>to mock him;</hi> that is, to abuſe and affront him. <hi>He will ſurely reprove you, if ye do ſecretly accept Perſons. Shall not his Excellency make you afraid, and his Dread fall upon you?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But indeed there needs no Authority to vouch for us in this Caſe. We may certainly conclude, without the Affirmation of an Apoſtle, or a Prophet, or any other Inſpired Winter, That this is a deteſtable Principle. 'Tis abſurd and ſelf-contradictory, and as directly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to all good Senſe and Reaſon, as any Principle can poſſibly be. To deſign, and to do good, is the proper buſineſs of an intelligent and reaſonable Being. 'Tis the Glory of God Himſelf, and 'tis what he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires of all, whom he hath made after his own Image. Now <hi>that</hi> is <hi>good</hi> for an intelligent Creature, either to deſign or do, which is according to the Will of the Creator, (his Will being the Rule and the Meaſure of Goodneſs;) So that <hi>to do Evil,</hi> in order to the <hi>doing Good,</hi> is to contradict and thwart his Will, in order to the performing it; 'tis to offend him, in order to plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing him; 'tis to break his Commandments, in order to the keeping them. In a word, 'tis to do that which is directly oppoſite to the end, which we profeſs to aim at. For no Evil has in its own Nature a Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency to Good, but to the juſt contrary. It may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed be over-rul'd (as you have heard) to other ends than thoſe to which it has a natural Tendency: But then this is not from the Nature of the Thing, but
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:54293:11"/>from the Wiſdom of God. The Event only is God's; but that does not alter the nature of the Action, which is to be meaſur'd by the Rule which God has given his Creatures to act by. But I think no more need be ſaid in ſo plain a Caſe.</p>
            <p>I know that 'tis commonly pretended by thoſe that act upon this Principle, That the Actions they do would not inded be good, but only as they are directed to ſuch an end; but that the Goodneſs of the End will San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctify the Means, and take off the evil that otherwiſe would naturally be in ſuch Actions. But let us try how this way of arguing will ſolve the Difficulty in any of the Inſtances already given.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Job</hi>'s Friends intended to juſtify, and ſo to Honour God, by accuſing their Friend, and laying to his charge what he was not guilty of. Their End was good; but it did not for all that, it ſeems, alter the nature of the Means. 'Twas ſtill <hi>ſpeaking wickedly for God, and talking deceitfully for him;</hi> it was <hi>mocking</hi> (or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronting) <hi>God,</hi> for which, as he there tells them, they were in danger of being <hi>ſearched out,</hi> and <hi>reproved</hi> by him. The <hi>Jews</hi> again propos'd to themſelves <hi>the doing God Service:</hi> But this did not render <hi>Killing</hi> of inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Men, no Murder. St. <hi>Paul verily thought that he ought to do</hi> what he did, for the Honour of God (no doubt) and the good of his Church: But yet this would not make <hi>Perſecution</hi> and <hi>Injurious Dealing,</hi> to become Innocent and Righteous Actions. And ſo again in our Text, he ſuppoſes that the Deſign may be, <hi>that Good may come;</hi> whilſt the Action in order to that end is <hi>Evil,</hi> and thereupon deteſts the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple.</p>
            <p>The Truth of this matter is in ſhort this. There are ſome Actions ſo manifeſtly unlawful in their own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:54293:12"/>that they cannot be made lawful by being deſign'd to bring about the beſt End that can be thought of. There are ſome Actions ſo plainly contrary to the Laws of God, and to the Reaſon and Nature of Things eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh'd by him, that they muſt not be done upon any account whatſoever.</p>
            <p>And now to Apply this to our preſent Purpoſe, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly to that Conſpiracy which firſt gave occaſion for the Obſervation of <hi>this Day.</hi> There can be no great doubt made, whether it were begun and carried on upon this deteſtable Principle, which the Apoſtle renounces in the Text, and declares to be <hi>damnable.</hi> 'Tis true, the Actors in it did not avow, That they thought it lawful <hi>to do Evil, that Good might come.</hi> No; they ſaid, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Pretence I juſt now ſuggeſted, That ſo Excellent an End as theirs was, could not chuſe but ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtify the Means they were about to uſe in order to it. And therefore, though from the Remains of Reaſon and Good Nature, ſome of them ſtartled at the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of bringing about their End, yet that Scruple was overcome by the Zeal they had for the Intereſts of their Church and Religion. Wherein, by the way, we ſee the danger of being engaged in a Falſe Religion; and particularly, how much the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> has de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauch'd the Conſciences of thoſe that have been tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough pac'd in their Profeſſion. But need we ſtand to prove that theſe were unlawful, nay, wicked and abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable Means, whatever their End might be? Was it no Crime then, at one Blow to deſtroy the Lives of ſo many innocent Perſons, who had not the leaſt appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of their Danger? Was it no Crime to offer Violence to the Perſon of the King, and thoſe of the Eſtates of the Kingdom aſſembled in Parliament? To
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:54293:12"/>cut off the Flower of our Nobility and Gentry at once, and upon that to involve the whole Nation in Confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Slaughter, and Blood; which muſt neceſſarily have enſued, as ſoon as the <hi>deadly Blow</hi> had been given? Good God! That ever Human Nature ſhould be capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of being thus wrought upon, to throw off all the Principles and Inclinations of Humanity! And that ever any Men, in order to advance Reveal'd Religion, ſhould thus directly contradict and violate all that is Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural! The mere naming theſe things, without com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting upon them, is abundantly ſufficient to declare the Wickedneſs of the Means they uſed.</p>
            <p>And after all, What was the End to be brought about by theſe Means, which might be able to ſanctify them, and to purge out the Evil that was naturally in them? Why, here's the miſchief, and thus commonly it falls out, That thoſe who make uſe of ſuch kind of Means as theſe, under the Pretence of purſuing ſome worthy End, are as groſly miſtaken about their End, as they are about the Means. 'Tis indeed an obſervable Inſtance of the Divine Juſtice towards men, in thus blinding their eyes, and hardening their hearts, in <hi>gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them up to ſtrong deluſions, that they may believe a lye,</hi> when they do not ſincerely and heartily love the Truth. They commonly firſt propoſe to themſelves very wicked Ends, and then no wonder if they chuſe Means that are equally wicked. And thus it was in this caſe. The End was to root out God's true Religion from amongſt us, and to reeſtabliſh the Errors and evil Practices of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, which had been juſtly diſcarded by us. Had <hi>their</hi> Religion been true, and <hi>ours</hi> falſe, nothing but a <hi>ſtrong Deluſion</hi> could have led them to the taking this courſe, for the introducing the one, and the rooting out the other. It cannot be
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:54293:13"/>from God, with his approbation, or allowance, that men ſhould violate thoſe Laws of his, which are ſo plainly written in our very Nature; that they ſhould renounce all Juſtice and Mercy, and put off Humanity it ſelf, for the Advancement of the trueſt Religion, or the beſt Church in the world. And what then ſhall be ſaid, when the greateſt Barbarities are exerciſed, for the eſtabliſhing Error, Superſtition, and Idolatry; for the ruining an Excellent Church, and the ſubverting a well-order'd Government? We may very well ſay, in the Words of our Text, Thoſe who preſume to do <hi>Evil,</hi> that ſuch <hi>Good may come, their Damnation is juſt.</hi> But let us paſs from this, to the laſt Obſervation I laid down from the Words, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">III. That it is a <hi>ſlanderous,</hi> and therefore a very <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt</hi> and <hi>deteſtable</hi> Practice, to charge this Principle up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe who not only diſown it, but whoſe Actions have given no juſt occaſion for ſuch an Imputation.</p>
            <p>This is in truth ſo lewd a Principle, that thoſe who do act upon it, will probably not be ſo hardy as to own that they do ſo. But however, if they do evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently act upon it, then 'tis no Slander, no Injuſtice to ſay they do. But if, on the contrary, they not only diſavow the Principle, but have given no juſt ground for ſuch a Charge, then it is without all queſtion a <hi>ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous Report.</hi> So St. <hi>Paul</hi> affirms in the Text, uſing the ſame word, which, when applied to God, is ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd <hi>Blaſphemy,</hi> and when to Men, 'tis tranſlated by <hi>evil ſpeaking,</hi> or (as here) by <hi>ſlanderouſly reporting,</hi> or <hi>calumniating.</hi> And he adds, <hi>Whoſe damnation is juſt;</hi> by which, as I took notice in the Explication of the Text, ſome underſtand his meaning to have been, That thoſe <hi>Jews</hi> who rais'd this <hi>ſlanderous Report</hi> upon the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:54293:13"/>Apoſtles, when they did, or at leaſt might eaſily, if it had not been their own fault, have known that it was <hi>a ſlander,</hi> were <hi>juſtly liable to damnation</hi> for ſo doing; ſo that God would puniſh them, not only for rejecting the Goſpel when preach'd to them, but alſo for <hi>calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niating</hi> the Doctrine of Chriſtianity, and <hi>ſlandering</hi> its Preachers.</p>
            <p>I need not ſtand to prove the Truth of the Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Every one will readily allow it, that to lay ſo ſoul an Imputation upon any that have not deſerved it, is the worſt ſort of <hi>Calumny</hi> and <hi>Injuſtice.</hi> But the reaſon of my mentioning it, is, both becauſe it is evidently implied in the Text, and becauſe there are <hi>Some who have ſlanderouſly reported and affirmed,</hi> That We of this Church and Nation have acted upon this Principle, and this particularly in One of thoſe Inſtances which we have made a new Reaſon for our aſſembling at this Time.</p>
            <p>They own indeed, That the Preſervation of our Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and our Religion in our Fathers days, was a ſignal Act of Divine Providence, for which we ought ſtill to expreſs our Thankfulneſs: But they ſay, That our late Deliverance, however permitted by God for wiſe and good Ends, was nevertheleſs brought about by unlawful Means; ſo that inſtead of rendring Thanks to God, as we now do, we ought rather to humble our ſelves before Him for the great Tranſgreſſion we have been guilty of. I thus plainly relate what has been too often ſaid upon this occaſion; which, if it were not notorious, ought not to have been mentioned. But ſeeing ſome have the Confidence thus to charge us, it ſeems reaſonable, nay, neceſſary on ſuch Occaſions as this, to ſhew that the Imputation is falſe and <hi>ſlanderous,</hi> and this partly, to do right to our ſelves; partly, for
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:54293:14"/>the fortifying ſuch as may be liable to be ſhockt by the bold Aſſertions of Confident Men; and partly for the convincing thoſe amongſt them, whoſe Prejudices and Paſſions have not ſet them out of the reach of all calm and ſober Reaſoning.</p>
            <p>To come to the point therefore with <hi>the Reporters of this ſlander.</hi> The ſecond Occaſion of this Solemnity was the happy Arrival of His Preſent Majeſty on <hi>this Day</hi> for the Deliverance of our Church and Nation. It was, I am ſure, an Arrival which was eagerly deſired and expected by a conſiderable number of thoſe, who have appear'd diſſatisfied at the Event. By the ſoberer part of them, I think it is not now made a Matter of Diſpute, Whether our Laws, and Liberties, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, were at That time in imminent Danger, or not; nor whether His Majeſty's Undertaking were not very deſirable, in order to the reſcuing us from the Evils we then fear'd were coming upon us. But according to theſe Mens preſent Apprehenſions, we did not, it ſeems, make a right uſe of the Bleſſing which Providence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow'd upon us; that is, things were order'd and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in ſuch manner, as prov'd contrary to their expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and to ſome Schemes which they had form'd to themſelves. Well, be it ſo for once: But who was it that made this Settlement for us? Even Thoſe who alone at that time were in a Capacity of doing it. We were firſt reduced to that State, that we wanted ſome Deliverer from Abroad; we were generally deſirous of his Speedy Arrival among us; ſoon after his Arrival we were left in a ſtate of Anarchy and Confuſion, and put under a new Neceſſity of taking up ſome ſpeedy and effectual Reſolutions of ſecuring the Publick Peace; we were by thoſe who had through their unhappy Management firſt brought us to theſe ſtraits, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:54293:14"/>deſerted us in the midſt of them, left to do the beſt we could for our ſelves. Now I would fain know of our diſaffected Countreymen, Who in ſuch a Caſe muſt determine what was to be done? When <hi>the Legal Conſtitution,</hi> whereby any Society or Body of Men is held together, is once broken, let it be by what means it will, there are but two ways, that I can think of, to bring things to an Iſſue; <hi>viz.</hi> Either <hi>Fighting</hi> or <hi>Voting.</hi> The latter certainly is the more <hi>Human</hi> way of the two, and ſuch as it much better becomes <hi>Reaſonable</hi> Creatures to uſe, than the former; and if once matters come to a Publick <hi>Vote,</hi> as in this Caſe of ours they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily did, <hi>the Law of Reaſon,</hi> which is Eternal and Immutable, dictates, That the Leſſer Part ſhould yield to the Greater; and this ſo, that in all matters of purely <hi>Civil Right,</hi> every Private Man is in reaſon bound, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſubmit to the Major Vote, or to leave the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, or to be contented with what they ſhall pleaſe to inflict upon him for his Singularity. This is ſo plain a Caſe, that it often ſeems to me matter of wonder, and what is not to be accounted for from any Reaſon, but is to be reſolv'd into the mere ſtrength of Prejudice, That men otherwiſe of good Senſe and Meaning, ſhould not be thoroughly convinc'd by this Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Inſomuch that thoſe who ſtand off from our preſent Eſtabliſhment, and will not own themſelves Subjects to this Government, are, as far as I can per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, the only Body of Men that ever yet diſſented from <hi>an Eſtabliſh'd Government,</hi> upon their Principles. Had they been <hi>Conquer'd,</hi> that is, compell'd by down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Force of Arms, as far as I underſtand their Scheme, they might have yielded upon their own Principles. But let them conſider this Matter fairly once again.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:54293:15"/>
            <p> The Nation, thanks be to God, was not <hi>Conquer'd;</hi> ſo far from that, that this Revolution was not only made and eſtabliſh'd by our <hi>Repreſentatives</hi> freely cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen and aſſembled, but what they did, I take to be agreeable to the Senſe of the far Greater and Better Part of the Kingdom; ſo that it is <hi>Conſent,</hi> not <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt,</hi> upon which the preſent Eſtabliſhment is plainly founded. But after all, the profeſs'd <hi>Enemies</hi> of the Government are, I hope, <hi>Conquer'd.</hi> They were firſt <hi>out voted,</hi> and they are ever ſince <hi>over-power'd</hi> and <hi>over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rul'd;</hi> and if they will not allow themſelves after all this to be <hi>conquer'd,</hi> it muſt be only becauſe the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment has been ſo gentle, as not to let them <hi>feel</hi> that they are ſo. But one would think, that Wiſe Men ſhould rather chuſe to be conquer'd in this gentle and eaſy way, and that Ingenuity ſhould work upon them, where the utmoſt Force is ſpar'd. And this, I think, is all that is neceſſary to be ſaid, for the Vindication of Thoſe that are mere <hi>Subjects,</hi> or for the Satisfaction of Thoſe that ought to be ſo.</p>
            <p>As to the <hi>Government</hi> it ſelf, and particularly the <hi>States</hi> of the Nation, who firſt in <hi>Convention,</hi> when Neceſſity requir'd, and afterwards in a <hi>Parliament</hi> call'd according to the Forms of Law, have determin'd things as they are, it would be as preſumptuous, as 'tis need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, to pretend to Apologize for them. The <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> thanks be to God, is, and I hope always will be, able to vindicate it ſelf againſt all that ſhall preſume openly to affront or calumniate it. All therefore that I ſhall farther add upon this Subject, is to put a few ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Queſtions to thoſe that ſpeak evil of us; and they are theſe.</p>
            <p>Whether before the happy Arrival of his Majeſty on <hi>this Day,</hi> our Laws and Liberties, and particularly our
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:54293:15"/>Religion eſtabliſh'd by Law, were not in the utmoſt danger?</p>
            <p>Whether at the ſame time, the Liberties of <hi>Europe,</hi> and the Proteſtant Religion in general, were not in the ſame danger?</p>
            <p>Whether we did not then earneſtly wiſh and pray, That Providence would find out ſome way for our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance? And whether it was not fit and reaſonable that we ſhould do ſo?</p>
            <p>Whether, when Providence ſtirr'd up a Neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Prince and State to yield us their Aſſiſtance, it were reaſonable for us to refuſe it? Nay, Whether it had not been high Ingratitude to Almighty God, and to his Inſtrument in our Deliverance, as well as great Folly with reſpect to our ſelves, and a ſtupid and ſenſleſs Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regard of our own and our Neighbour's Welfare, if we had not thankfully receiv'd and embrac'd it?</p>
            <p>Let me ask them farther, Whether the <hi>Fundamental Conſtitution</hi> of a Government may not be ſo violated, and the <hi>Regular</hi> and <hi>Legal</hi> ſtate of things ſo ſhook and diſorder'd, that the <hi>Law of Reaſon,</hi> which is ever ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior to all <hi>Particular Forms</hi> and <hi>Conſtitutions</hi> of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ought to take place?</p>
            <p>And, Whether, when we were reduced to ſuch Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, that both the <hi>Repreſentatives</hi> and the <hi>Body</hi> of this Nation took it to be our Caſe, they might not, nay, they ought not, to ſettle things for the future in the beſt manner they could?</p>
            <p>And laſtly, Whether this being done, every good man ought not to acquieſce under, nay, be thankful for ſuch a Settlement? Theſe things I leave to be ſeriouſly weigh'd by them, whenever they are in Temper to conſider.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:54293:16"/>
            <p> And now what remains, as the Cloſe of all, but that reflecting upon both theſe Deliverances together, we render our hearty Thanks and Praiſe to Almighty God, as the principal Author of them? There is indeed very much of the Wiſdom and Goodneſs of God to be contemplated in both Inſtances; the Conſideration of which ſhould inſpire us with a hearty Thankfulneſs to him for what is paſt, and with a good Hope in him for the future. We may juſtly upon this Occaſion uſe the words of <hi>Moſes</hi> in his Song, upon the occaſion of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> being delivered from the purſuit of <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Hoſt, and reſcued from the Danger they were in of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing either carried back into <hi>Egypt,</hi> or cut off by the way; <hi>The Lord is my ſtrength and ſong,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod 15.2.</note> 
               <hi>and he is become my ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; he is my God, and I will glorify him; my father's God, and I will exalt him.</hi> We may again ſay with the <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi> upon occaſion of another Deliverance of that People;
<note place="margin">Pſal. 48.8.</note> 
               <hi>As we have heard, ſo have we ſeen, in the city of the Lord of hoſts, in the city of our God; God ſhall eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh it for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if we heartily deſire that God may Eſtabliſh us, we ought to expreſs our Thankfulneſs ſome better way, than meerly by Words. If our Senſe of the Divine Goodneſs be real, it will produce ſome real effects upon us; and if our deſires of the continuance of the Divine Favour to our Church and Nation are in earneſt, they will put us upon uſing all the means that are proper on our part, in order to that end; particularly,</p>
            <p n="1">1. As we give thanks to God, for the preſerving our <hi>Legal Government,</hi> and therewith our <hi>Liberties</hi> and <hi>Properties</hi> to us; ſo let us manifeſt our juſt Value for theſe Bleſſings, by a wiſe and ſober uſe of them. Let us endeavour the Eſtabliſhing this Government,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:54293:16"/>by diſcharging the Duties of our ſeveral places under it. Let thoſe that are Magiſtrates put the wholeſome Laws in Execution, eſpecially againſt ſuch Practices as may provoke the Wrath of Almighty God againſt us. Let each private Man Obey the Laws of his Countrey, and Honour the Perſons of Governors and Magiſtrates, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the account of the Characters and Offices they bear. Let every one of us excite in himſelf an inward Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern for the <hi>Publick Good,</hi> for the Welfare of <hi>the whole Body;</hi> preferring this, as it becomes us, before all pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate and particular Intereſts. Let us lay aſide all Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous contending for Parties, and promote Concord and Unanimity as much as is poſſible; remembring Who hath told us, That <hi>every Kingdom divided againſt it ſelf is brought to Deſolation; and every City divided againſt it ſelf ſhall not ſtand,</hi> Matth. 12.25.</p>
            <p>Let us again have a care of abuſing our Liberty to any kind of Licentiouſneſs; and particularly let us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of running into the Extreme, which is directly oppoſite to <hi>that</hi> we have ſo lately avoided. Conſidering how prone Mankind are to run from one Extreme to the other, it may not be amiſs for us, who have been within theſe few Years ſcar'd with the Fears of <hi>Arbitrary</hi> and <hi>Lawleſs Power,</hi> to be watchful over our ſelves, leſt we ſhould throw off that Reverence which is juſtly due to Government. Obedience and Submiſſion to Authority (I mean always that which is <hi>Legally</hi> ſo, according to the particular Conſtitution of each Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey) is an indiſpenſable Duty, both according to Reaſon and Scripture: And there is no leſs danger to the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick; nay, in ſo well-temper'd a Conſtitution as Ours, I doubt the danger is ordinarily greater, from the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dutifulneſs of Subjects, than from the Arbitrarineſs of Governors. A <hi>Legal Government,</hi> ſuch as Ours is, is
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:54293:17"/>the juſt Middle between the two Extremes; and we ought both from Reaſon, and from the Experience we have had in this Nation, to beware of both alike.</p>
            <p>But this I ſpeak by way of Caution only; hoping and believing better things, not only of thoſe that now hear me, but of the Body of our Nation in General; who have, notwithſtanding the late preſſing Difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties we have been under, and thoſe eſpecially upon the more ordinary ſort of People among us, maintain'd a ſteady Loyalty to our Governors; and, to the great Regret of our Enemies, ſhewn, That we are not ſo giddy and unconſtant, as they would either repreſent us, or perſuade us to be.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As we give Thanks to God for the Preſervation of our Religion; Let us likewiſe expreſs our juſt Value for ſo ineſtimable a Bleſſing, by ſuffering it to have its due effect upon our Temper and our Lives.</p>
            <p>The only reaſon why the <hi>Reform'd Religion</hi> is ſo much to be prefer'd before the <hi>Romiſh,</hi> is becauſe it tends to make us better Men. And it had been much better for us to have been bred in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> or to have had the Ignorance and Errors of Popery intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced again amongſt us; unleſs we improve the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages we have by the Reformation, to the Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Manners. It would then have been ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe to us, that we had known no better; whereas now being plainly inſtructed in our Duty, 'twill be a high Aggravation of our Guilt, if we refuſe to comply with it. The deſign of all true Religion, is to render us ſober and chaſt, modeſt and humble, juſt and charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, pious and devout, more like to God, and more like Gods one to another.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:54293:17"/>
            <p> And here again I cannot forbear recommending Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord and Unanimity, which are altogether as uſeful and neceſſary, with reſpect to our <hi>Religious,</hi> as to our <hi>Civil</hi> Intereſts. 'Tis a Melancholy Conſideration, That ſince the firſt Reformation of our Church, we are crumbled into ſo many Parties and Diviſions. The Eſtabliſh'd Church is the very ſame that it was in the Glorious Reign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> which we ſo frequently and ſo juſtly admire and magnify; and the Terms of Communion are the very ſame now, that they were then.</p>
            <p>If we trace our Diviſions to the beginning, and exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine how the <hi>Tares</hi> of Diſſention came to be ſow'd among us; the Anſwer muſt be that which our Saviour hath taught us in the Parable, <hi>The Enemy did this,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 13.24.</note> 
               <hi>whilſt we were ſleeping.</hi> And ſurely after ſo long Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of the Enemy's Deſigns upon us, we ought to awake, and to learn at leaſt this neceſſary piece of Wiſdom, To render our ſelves firm againſt all future Attempts, by a cloſer Union amongſt our ſelves.</p>
            <p>And this will appear the more neceſſary at this time, if we conſider the danger we are in upon the ſame ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count from Adverſaries of another ſort. I mean, ſome that have no regard for any Religion, or at leaſt not for that which is Reveal'd; and others, who though they profeſs themſelves <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> yet preſume not only to Diſpute and Cavil at, but to ridicule and expoſe to Contempt all the <hi>Myſteries</hi> of our Chriſtian Faith.</p>
            <p>When I ſpeak of Union, I do not think it is to be expected, that we ſhould be all preſently of one mind in all things. But it were to be hoped, That among other good effects of the late Happy Revolution, we, who were delivered from <hi>a Common Enemy,</hi> might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come better Friends to one another, 'Tis certainly our
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:54293:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>Duty and our Intereſt on all ſides to do what in us lies towards the becoming <hi>One Body</hi> in <hi>Church</hi> as well as in <hi>State;</hi> and if every one among us would but do juſt as much as <hi>in Conſcience</hi> he can towards this, our Diviſions, I am perſuaded, would not continue much longer, at leaſt they would quickly be much ſewer than they are.</p>
            <p>To conclude; Let us not willingly differ in any thing but Mind, and Speak, and Do the ſame things; and where, after our beſt endeavours, our Judgments ſtill happen to differ, there let our Charity and Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Forbearance take place. For though I am very ſure 'tis the Duty and the Intereſt of Chriſtians to be of one Mind, and of one Communion; yet 'tis certainly as great a Duty, and I think a greater Perfection, to maintain Chriſtian Charity in the midſt of our Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences.</p>
            <p>I ſhall ſhut up my Exhortation with that Apoſtolical Precept, which carries both Reaſon and Authority in it;
<note place="margin">Phil. 3.15, 16.</note> 
               <hi>Let us therefore as many as are perfect, be thus mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: And if in any thing ye be otherwiſe minded, may God reveal even this unto you. Nevertheleſs whereto we have already attained, let us walk by the ſame Rule; let us mind the ſame thing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now to the God of Peace and Concord, the Great Author of that Peace which we enjoy, the Founder and Protector of that Holy Religion which we Profeſs; To God even our Father, and to the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the Only-begotten of the Father, with the Eternal Spirit, be aſcribed as is moſt due, all Praiſe and Glory, now and for ever.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
